Finding Aid for University Musical Society (University of Michigan) records, 1879-2009.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- President's and Executive Director's Correspondence 1928, 1930-1935, 1984-1988
  - President Gail W. Rector
    - 1985 (Box 116)
      - W, X Y Z (Box 116)
    - 1986
      - A (Box 116)
      - Ann Arbor Summer Festival (Box 116)
      - Arts Midwest grants (Box 116)
      - B (Box 116)
      - Big Ten Concert Managers (Box 116)
      - Board of Directors (Box 116)
      - C (Box 116)
      - D (Box 116)
      - Encore (Box 116)
      - F, G (Box 116)
      - H, I (Box 116)
        (includes Rotary address by Ramon Hernandez, director Ann Arbor Public Library about family connection to May Festival)
      - Inquiries from artists and managers (Box 116)
      - Intra-university (Box 117)
      - J, K, L (Box 117)
      - M, N (Box 117)
      - O, P (Box 117)
      - Orchestra Hall, Rector consultant (Box 117)
      - R, S (Box 117)
      - Search Committee for UMS director 1985, 1986 (Box 117)
      - T, U, V (Box 117)
      - W (Box 117)
      - X, Y, Z (Box 117)
    - 1987
      (Gail Rector, President; Kenneth Fischer, Executive Director)
      - A (Box 117)
      - Advisory Committee (Box 117)
      - Arts Midwest grants (Box 117)
      - Ann Arbor Summer Festival (Box 117)
      - B (Box 117)
      - Big Ten Concert Managers (Box 117)
      - Board of Directors (Box 117)
      - C (Box 117)
      - Chronological, June-September (Box 117)
      - Chronological, October-December (Box 117)
      - D, E (Box 117)
      - Encore (Box 117)
      - F, G (Box 117)
      - H, I (Box 117)
      - Inquiries from artists and managers (Box 117)
      - Intra university (Box 117)
      - J, K, L (Box 117)
      - M (Box 117)
      - N (Box 117)
      - O, P (Box 117)
      - R, S (Box 117)
      - T, U, V (Box 117)
      - X, Y, Z (Box 117)
  - Kenneth Fischer, Executive Director
    - 1988
      - A, B (Box 118)
      - C, includes Columbia Artists Management, Inc. (CAMI) (Box 118)
      - Chronological files 1988, 2 folders (Box 118)
      - D, F (Box 118)
      - G, H (Box 118)
      - I (Box 118)
      - International Society of Performing Arts Administrators (ISPAA) (Box 118)
      - J, K, L (Box 118)
      - M (Box 118)
      - N, O, P (Box 118)
      - R, S (Box 118)
      - T, U (Box 118)
- Staff Files 1990-1995
  The Staff Files series documents the efforts of the Education and Audience Development staff and of the Events and Donor Relations staff. Educational packets for 1995/96 and 1996/97 and correspondence and planning related to development events are included in this series.
  - Events and Donor Relations
    - May Festival 1990-1995, 6 folders (Box 118)
    - Benefit Auction 1991, 1992 (Box 118)
    - Cheers 1992/93 (Box 118)
    - Volunteers, 1992 1993 (Box 118)
- Executive Director's Files 1987-1993
  The Presidents' Topical Files series includes documentation from the years 1964-1973 of Gail Rector's tenure, and the years 1987-1994 of Kenneth Fischer's tenure. The files are not broken by year. The folder "Hill Auditorium Renovation, 1990-1992" contains a detailed "History of Hill Auditorium At the University of Michigan" by Ernest O. Moore written for the Office of the University Planner in 1978. The "Love Letters" folders contain congratulatory letters and letters thanking Kenneth Fischer and the UMS staff from performers, patrons, community leaders, impresario colleagues and musical professionals, members of the UM and Ann Arbor communities and friends. Thank you letters were sent for tickets received, presentations made, for community service performed, and, in general, for the quality of presentations provided by the University Musical Society.
  - Kenneth Fischer 1987-1994
    - American Society of Association Executives (ASAE) 1987 (Box 119)
    - Auction 1990, 1993 (Box 119)
    - Board of Directors and Committees 1987/88-1991/92, 4 folders (Box 119)
    - Choral Union 1987-1991 (Box 119)
    - Development 1988-1991 (Box 119)
    - Finances June 1987-November 1992 (Box 119)
    - Hill Auditorium Renovation 1990-1992 (Box 119)
    - Israel Philharmonic 1991 (Box 119)
    - Leonard Bernstein/Vienna Philharmonic 1988 (Box 119)
    - Letters from customers 1987-1988 (Box 119)
    - Long Range Planning Committee 1990/91-1991/92, 2 folders (Box 119)
    - "Love letters" (congratulatory letters)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 119)
      - 1989 (Box 119)
      - 1990 (Box 119)
      - 1991 (Box 119)
      - 1992 (Box 119)
      - 1993 (Box 120)
      - 1994 (Box 120)
    - Marketing 1987-1991 (Box 120)
    - May Festival
      - 1988 (Box 120)
      - 1991 (Box 120)
      - 100th Anniversary 1993 (Box 120)
      - Questionnaire 1994 (Box 120)
    - Meetings with Norm Herbert 1991-1992 (Box 120)
    - Metropolitan Opera Orchestra Benefit Concert 1991 (Box 120)
    - Michigan MozartFest/Norrington 1988-1990 (Box 120)
    - Office remodeling 1988-1991 (Box 120)
    - Pre-concert presentations 1987 1990- 1992/93 (Box 120)
    - Speeches, slide presentations 1968, 1991 (Box 120)
    - Stratford Festival/Ann Arbor November 1993, 1991-1993 (Box 120)
    - Student paper on UMS 1991 (Box 120)
    - Ushers, 1988- 1992/93 (Box 120)
    - "Welcome" correspondence, news clippings 12/1986, 1/1987 (Box 120)
    - Youth Program 1991, 1992 (Box 120)
- Scripts
  The Scripts series includes rehearsal scripts from Royal Shakespeare Company productions in 2002 and 2006. Scripts include Midnight's Children (2002), Anthony and Cleopatra (2006), Julius Caesar (2006) and The Tempest (2006).
  - Royal Shakespeare Company (Box 122)
    - The Tempest, November 2006 (Box 122)
    - Midnight's Children, 2002 (Box 122)
    - Antony and Cleopatra, 2006 (Box 122)
    - Julius Caesar, 2006 (Box 122)
- Motion Pictures (Film, Videotape and DVD)
  The Video Recordings (2 linear feet) document various performances sponsored by the University Musical Society. Formats include VHS videotapes, and DVCAM and DAT digital video tapes. The VHS tapes include the Distinguished Artist Award of the Ford Honors Program (1996-1998 and 2001-2002), the Hill Auditorium Re-opening Concert in January 2004, special performances by the Grand Rapids Symphony, and the Youth Performance Series (2001-2003). The Royal Shakespeare Company (RSC) residency videotapes include lectures by Ralph Williams, professor of English Language and Literature at the University of Michigan, delivered prior to the performance of the history plays in 2001 and the Merry Wives of Windsor and Coriolanus in 2003. There are several tapes documenting the RSC performance of Salman Rushdie's work Midnight's Children. A copy of the rehearsal script will be found in the Scripts series. DVDs documents a performance by singing group Sweet Honey in the Rock at Hill Auditorium in 2004, the 2004 Merce Cunningham Residency, and Distinguished Artist awards.
  Also in the Motion Pictures series is a 16mm film entitled A Conductor Speaks featuring Arthur Fiedler and Gail Rector. An interview with legendary UM band director William Revelli is also captured on videotape.
  - Films
    - A Conductor Speaks 1972 (Box 110)
      (Arthur Fiedler and Gail Rector)
  - Video Recordings
    - Hill Auditorium Exterior Details April 1993 (Box 111)
    - Remembrances of Hill Auditorium, Interview with Charlotte McGeoch May 16, 1993 (Box 111)
    - Interview with Alva Sink March 16, 1993 (Box 111)
    - Interview with William D. Revelli March 30, 1993 (Box 111)
    - Dance 2001-2002, VHS (Box 122)
    - Distinguished Artist Award (Ford Honors Program), VHS
      - Van Cliburn 1996 (Box 122)
      - Jessye Norman 1997 (Box 122)
      - Garrick Ohlsson 1998 (Box 122)
      - Marcel Marceau 2001 (Box 122)
      - Marilyn Horne 2002, 2 tapes (Box 122)
    - Hill Auditorium Re-Opening Concert 2004, VHS (Box 122)
    - Royal Shakespeare Company 2001, VHS
      - Lectures, January-February, 4 tapes (Box 122)
      - Tetralogy Audience Before the Show, March (Box 122)
    - Royal Shakespeare Company 2003, VHS (Box 123)
      - Lectures, February-March (Box 123)
      - Roundtable Discussions on Coriolanus and Merry Wives of Windsor, March (Box 123)
      - Midnight's Children
        - Simon Reade February 2004 (Box 123)
        - Roundtable March 2003 (Box 123)
        - Salman Rushdie Interview by Anhutosh Vashney March 2003 (Box 123)
        - Symposium (Internet) Panel Discussion March 2003 (Box 123)
        - Conversation and Reading by Rushdie with Gauri Viswanathan March 2003 (Box 123)
      - Special Performances Grand Rapids Symphony undated, VHS (Box 123)
      - A Tribute to Gospel Legend Mattie Moss Clark 2002 (Box 123)
    - Youth Performance Series 2001-2003, 2 tapes VHS (Box 123)
  - DVD Recordings
    - Ford Honors Program May 13, 2006
      - UMS Distinguished Artist Award to Dave Brubeck May 13, 2006, DVD (Box 123)
    - Ford Honors Program January 24, 2009
      - UMS Distinguished Artist Award to Sir James Galway May 10, 2008, DVD (Box 123)
    - Ford Honors Program January 24, 2009
      - Gala Event January 24, 2009, DVD (Box 123)
      - UMS Distinguished Artist Award to Ralph Williams January 24, 2009, DVD (Box 123)
      - Tribute to Education January 24, 2009, DVD (Box 123)
      - Tribute to Ralph Williams January 24, 2009, DVD (Box 123)
      - Tribute to Royal Shakespeare Company and Michael Boyd January 24, 2009, DVD (Box 123)
      - Tribute to Ralph Williams, Michael Boyd, Royal Shakespeare Company January 24, 2009, DVD (Box 123)
    - Merce Cunningham Residency March 8-13, 2004, DVD (Box 123)
    - Sound of the World Simon Shaheen Residency December 1, 2003-January 31, 2004, DVD (Box 123)
    - Sweet Honey in the Rock 2004, DVD (Box 123)
  - DV Recordings
    - Chicago Classical Oriental Ensemble February 8, 2008, DVCAM 3 tapes (Box 123)
    - Midnight's Children Events with Salman Rushdie 2003, DAT 5 tapes (Box 123)
- Sound Recordings
  Sound Recordings include material on cassette, CD, and LP formats. LP formats include the 100th anniversary celebration, and a 1978 recording of the performance of Messiah. CDs include Haydn's "The Creation," St. Matthew Passion," and William Bolcom's "Songs of Innocence and Experience."
  - Cassette
    - Daniella Mercury on WEMU April 11, 2003, 1 audiocassettes (Box 123)
  - CDs
    - Franz Joseph Haydn's "The Creation," April 2, 2005, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 123)
    - St. Matthew Passion, Detroit Symphony Orchestra, UMS Choral Union, MSU Children's Choir March 21, 2008, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 123)
    - UMS Choral Union, Handel's Messiah, Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra December 1, 2007, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 123)
    - UMS Choral Union, Three Sacred Pieces, All-Night Vigil, Op. 37, The Passing of the Year, Carmina Burana April 23, 2009, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 123)
    - William Bolcom: Songs of Innocence and of Experience 2004, 3 optical disks CDs
  - LPs
    - Messiah The University of Michigan Choral Union and the University Symphony Orchestra, December 1978, 1 phonograph records (Box 123)
      stored in Record Album location
    - Commemorating 100 Years The University of Michigan Symphony Orchestra Conducted by Yehudi Menuhin and Eugene Ormandy, 1979, 1 phonograph records (Box 123)
- Outsize Bound Volumes (BImu/N1)
  - Ledgers and Account Books, 7 volumes
    - Volume 1-Trial Balances 1904-1920 (Volume 1)
    - Volume 2-Journal 1916-1921 (Volume 2)
    - Volume 3-Journal 1921-1924 (Volume 3)
    - Volume 4-Journal 1924-1929 (Volume 4)
    - Volume 5-Journal 1929-1935 (Volume 5)
    - Volume 6-Journal 1935-1940 (Volume 6)
    - Volume 7-Ledger 1924-1939 (Volume 7)
- Outsize Scrapbooks
  The series Scrapbooks consist of two scrapbooks commemorating the 100th anniversary of the University Musical Society in 1979. "The University Choral Union", a yellow, 3-ring scrapbook, measures 13 x 19". It contains material dating from 1969 to 1979, including newspaper clippings, photographs, and programs concerning University Choral Union concerts and performers. "The Festival Chorus", a blue, 3-ring scrapbook, measures 13 x 20". It contains material dating from 1971 to 1979, including newspaper clippings, photographs, and programs documenting UMS concerts and performers.
  - Scrapbooks, 2 volumes
    - Volume 8-The Festival Chorus 1971-1979 (Volume 8)
    - Volume 9-The University Choral Union 1969-1979 (Volume 9)
- Outsize Photographs
  - Unidentified and Miscellaneous Photographs
    - Orchestra and Chorus undated, mounted on 18" x 30" board (Folder Bimul N1)
    - Orchestra and Chorus undated, mounted on 18" x 26" board (Folder Bimul N1)
    - Residence of Alexander Winchell which occupied the site where Hill Auditorium now stands, 12" x 21" (Folder Bimul N1)
    - Fiddle Sketch of Eugene Ormandy by Nathan Milstein, May 3, 10" x 13" (Folder Bimul N1)
  - Artists and Performance Photos
    - May Festival May 18-21, 1918, 21 photographs mounted on 22" x35" board (Folder Bimul N1)
    - Golden Jubilee May Festival with the Philadelphia Orchestra and Eugene Ormandy May 5-8, 1943, mounted on 13" x 21" board (Folder Bimul N1)
    - May 1946 Festival with the Philadelphia Orchestra and Eugene Ormandy, mounted on 12" x 21" board (Folder Bimul N1)
    - May 1946 Festival Youth Chorus, Philadelphia Orchestra, and Marguerite Hood (conductor), mounted on 10" x 21" board (Folder Bimul N1)
    - May 1951 Festival with the Philadelphia Orchestra and Thor Johnson (Folder Bimul N1)
Related Material
The Ann Arbor District Library and the University Musical Society have collaborated on an online collection of UMS programs and photographs titled UMS: A History of Great Performances. The site includes digitized, full-text searchable concert programs from 1879 to 1979 and a selection of photographs of performers, UMS staff, concert patrons, and venues.